the initials GPT stand for generative
pre-trained Transformer so that first
word is straightforward enough these are
Bots that generate new text pre-trained
refers to how the model went through a
process of learning from a massive
amount of data and the prefix insinuates
that there's more room to fine-tune it
on specific tasks with additional
training but the last word that's the
real key piece a Transformer is a
specific kind of neural network a
machine learning model and it's the core
invention underlying the current boom in
AI what I want to do with this video and
the following chapters is go through a
visually driven explanation for what
actually happens inside a Transformer
we're going to follow the data that
flows through it and go step by step
there are many different kinds of models
that you can build using Transformers
some models take in audio and produce a
transcript this sentence comes from a
model going the other way around
producing synthetic speech just from
text all those tools that took the World
by storm in 2022 like doll in
mid-journey that take in a text
description and produce an image are
based on Transformers and even if I
can't quite get it to understand what a
pie creature is supposed to be I'm still
blown away that this kind of thing is
even remotely possible and the original
Transformer introduced in 2017 by Google
was invented for the specific use case
of translating text from one language
into another but the variant that you
and I will focus on which is the type
that underlies tools like chat GPT will
be a model that's trained to take in in
a piece of text maybe even with some
surrounding images or sound accompanying
it and produce a prediction for what
comes next in the passage that
prediction takes the form of a
probability distribution over many
different chunks of text that might
follow at first glance you might think
that predicting the next word feels like
a very different goal from generating
new text but once you have a prediction
model like this a simple thing you could
try to make it generate a longer piece
of text is to give it an initial snippet
to work with have it take a random samp
Le from the distribution it just
generated append that sample to the text
and then run the whole process again to
make a new prediction based on all the
new text including what it just added I
don't know about you but it really
doesn't feel like this should actually
work in this animation for example I'm
running gpt2 on my laptop and having it
repeatedly predict and Sample the next
chunk of text to generate a story based
on the seed text and the story just
doesn't actually really make that much
sense but if I swap it out for API calls
to gpt3 in instead which is the same
basic model just much bigger suddenly
almost magically we do get a sensible
Story one that even seems to infer that
a pie creature would live in a Land of
math and computation this process here
of repeated prediction and sampling is
essentially what's happening when you
interact with chat GPT or any of these
other large language models and you see
them producing one word at a time in
fact one feature that I would very much
enjoy is the ability to see the
underlying distribution for each new
word that it chooses
let's kick things off with a very high
level preview of how data flows through
a Transformer we will spend much more
time motivating and interpreting and
expanding on the details of each step
but in Broad Strokes when one of these
chat Bots generates a given word here's
what's going on under the hood first the
input is broken up into a bunch of
little pieces these pieces are called
tokens and in the case of text these
tend to be words or little pieces of
words or other common character
combination
if images or sound are involved then
tokens could be little patches of that
image or little chunks of that sound
each one of these tokens is then
associated with a vector meaning some
list of numbers which is meant to
somehow encode the meaning of that piece
if you think of these vectors as giving
coordinates in some very high
dimensional space words with similar
meanings tend to land on vectors that
are close to each other in that space
this sequence of vectors then passes
through an operation that's known as an
attention block and this allows the
vectors to talk to each other and pass
information back and forth to update
their values for example the meaning of
the word model in the phrase a machine
learning model is different from its
meaning in the phrase a fashion model
the attention block is what's
responsible for figuring out which words
in the context are relevant to updating
the meanings of which other words and
how exactly those meanings should be
updated and again whenever I use the
word meaning this is somehow entirely
encoded in the entries of those
vectors after that the these vectors
pass through a different kind of
operation and depending on the source
that you're reading this will be
referred to as a multi-layer perceptron
or maybe a feed forward layer and here
the vectors don't talk to each other
they all go through the same operation
in parallel and while this block is a
little bit harder to interpret later on
we'll talk about how the step is a
little bit like asking a long list of
questions about each vector and then
updating them based on the answers to
those questions all of the operations in
both of these blocks look like a giant
pile of Matrix multiplic ations and our
primary job is going to be to understand
how to read the underlying
matrices I'm glossing over some details
about some normalization steps that
happen in between but this is after all
a high level preview after that the
process essentially repeats you go back
and forth between attention blocks and
multi-layer perceptron blocks until at
the very end the hope is that all of the
essential meaning of the passage has
somehow been baked into the very last
Vector in the sequence we then perform a
certain operation on that last Vector
that produces a probability distribution
over all possible tokens all possible
little chunks of text that might come
next and like I said once you have a
tool that predicts what comes next given
a snippet of text you can feed it a
little bit of seed text and have it
repeatedly play this game of predicting
what comes next sampling from the
distribution appending it and then
repeating over and over some of you in
the no may remember how long before chat
GPT came into the scene this is what
early demos of GPT 3 looked like you
would have it autocomplete stories and
essays based on an initial snippet to
make a tool like this into a chatbot the
easiest starting point is to have a
little bit of text that establishes the
setting of a user interacting with a
helpful AI assistant what you would call
the system prompt and then you would use
the user's initial question or prompt as
the first bit of dialogue and then you
have it start predicting what such a
helpful AI assistant would say in
response there is more to say about an
added step of training that's required
to make this work well but at a high
level this is the general
idea in this chapter you and I are going
to expand on the details of what happens
at the very beginning of the network at
the very end of the network and I also
want to spend a lot of time reviewing
some important bits of background
knowledge things that would have been
second nature to any machine learning
engineer by the time Transformers came
around if you're comfortable with that
background knowledge and a little
impatient you could probably feel free
to skip to the next chapter which is
going to focus on the atten blocks
generally considered the heart of the
Transformer after that I want to talk
more about these multi-layer perceptron
blocks how training works and a number
of other details that will have been
skipped up to that point for broader
context these videos are additions to a
minseries about deep learning and it's
okay if you haven't watched the previous
ones I think you can do it out of order
but before diving into Transformers
specifically I do think it's worth
making sure that we're on the same page
about the basic premise and structure of
deep learning at the risk of stating the
obvious this is one approach to machine
learning which describes any model where
you're using data to somehow determine
how a model behaves what I mean by that
is let's say you want a function that
takes in an image and it produces a
label describing it or our example of
predicting the next word given a passage
of text or any other task that seems to
require some element of intuition and
pattern recognition we almost take this
for granted these days but the idea with
machine learning is that rather than
trying to explicitly Define a procedure
for how to do that task in code which is
what people would have done in the
earliest days of AI instead you set up a
very flexible structure with tunable
parameters like a bunch of knobs and
dials and then somehow you use many
examples of what the output should look
like for a given input to tweak and tune
the values of those parameters to mimic
this behavior for example maybe the
simplest form of machine learning is
linear regression where your inputs and
your outputs are each single numbers
something like the square footage of a
house and its price and what you want is
to find a line of best fit through this
data you know to predict future house
prices that line is described by two
continuous parameters say the slope and
the Y intercept and the goal of linear
regression is to determine those
parameters to closely match the data
needless to say deep learning models get
much more complicated gpt3 for example
has not two but 175 billion parameters
but here's the thing it's it's not a
given that you can create some giant
model with a huge number of parameters
without it either grossly overfitting
the training data or being completely
intractable to train deep learning
describes a class of models that in the
last couple decades have proven to scale
remarkably well what unifies them is
that they all use the same training
algorithm it's called back propagation
we talked about it in previous chapters
and the context that I want you to have
as we go in is that in order for this
training algorithm to work well at scale
these models have to follow a certain
specific format and if you know this
format going in it helps to explain many
of the choices for how a Transformer
processes language which otherwise run
the risk of feeling kind of
arbitrary first whatever kind of model
you're making the input has to be
formatted as an array of real numbers
this could simply mean a list of numbers
it could be a two-dimensional array or
very often you deal with higher
dimensional arrays where the general
term used is tensor you often think of
that input data as being progressively
TR transformed into many distinct layers
where again each layer is always
structured as some kind of array of real
numbers until you get to a final layer
which you consider the output for
example the final layer in our text
processing model is a list of numbers
representing the probability
distribution for all possible next
tokens in deep learning these model
parameters are almost always referred to
as weights and this is because a key
feature of these models is that the only
way these parameters interact with the
data being processed is through weighted
sums you also sprinkle some nonlinear
functions throughout but they won't
depend on parameters typically though
instead of seeing the weighted sums all
naked and written out explicitly like
this you'll instead find them packaged
together as various components in a
matrix Vector
product it amounts to saying the same
thing if you think back to how Matrix
Vector multiplication Works each
component in the output it looks like a
weighted sum it's just often
conceptually cleaner for you and me to
think about matrices that are filled
with tunable parameters that transform
vectors that are drawn from the data
being
processed for example those 175 billion
weights in gpt3 are organized into just
under 28,000 distinct matrices those
matrices in turn fall into eight
different categories and what you and I
are going to do is Step through each one
of those categories to understand what
that type does as we go through I think
it's kind of fun to reference the
specific numbers from gpt3 to count up
exactly where those 75 billion come from
even if nowadays there are bigger and
better models this one has a certain
charm as the first large language model
to really capture the world's attention
outside of ml communities also
practically speaking companies tend to
keep much tighter lips around the
specific numbers for more modern
networks I just want to set the scene
going in that as you peek under the hood
to see what happens inside a tool like
chat GPT almost all of the actual
computation looks like Matrix Vector
multiplication there's a little bit of a
risk getting lost in the sea of billions
of numbers but you should draw a very
sharp distinction in your mind between
the weights of the model which I'll
always color in blue or red and the data
being processed which I'll always color
in Gray the weights are the actual
brains they are the things learned
during training and they determine how
it behaves the data being processed
simply encodes whatever specific input
is fed into the model for a given run
like an example snippet of
text with all of that as Foundation
let's dig into the first step of this
text processing example which is to
break up the input into little chunks
and turn those chunks into vectors I
mentioned how those chunks are called
tokens which might be pieces of words or
punctuation but every now and then in
this chapter and especially in the next
one I'd like to just pretend that it's
broken more cleanly into words because
we humans think in words this will just
make it much easier to reference little
examples and clarify each step the model
has a predefined vocabulary some list of
all possible words say 50,000 of them
and the first Matrix that we'll
encounter known as the embedding Matrix
has a single column for each one of
these
words these columns are what determines
what Vector each word turns into in that
first
step we label it we and like all the
matrices we see its values begin random
but they're going to be learned Based on
data turning words into vectors was
common practice in machine learning long
before Transformers but it's a little
little weird if you've never seen it
before and it sets the foundation for
everything that follows so let's take a
moment to get familiar with it we often
call this embedding a word which invites
you to think of these vectors very
geometrically as points in some
high-dimensional space visualizing a
list of three numbers as coordinates for
points in 3D space would be no problem
but word embeddings tend to be much much
higher dimensional in gpt3 they have
12,288 dimensions and as you'll see it
matters to work in a space that has a
lot of distinct directions in the same
way that you could take a
two-dimensional slice through a 3D space
and project all the points onto that
slice for the sake of animating word
embeddings that a simple model is giving
me I'm going to do an analogous Thing by
choosing a three-dimensional slice
through this very high dimensional space
and projecting the word vectors down
onto that and displaying the results the
big idea here is that as a model tweaks
and tunes its weights to determine how
exactly words get embedded as vectors
during training it tends to settle on a
set of embeddings where directions in
the space have a kind of semantic
meaning for the simple word to Vector
model I'm running here if I run a search
for all the words whose embeddings are
closest to that of tower you'll notice
how they all seem to give very similar
Tower is Vibes and if you want to pull
up some Python and play along at home
this is the specific model that I'm
using to make the animations it's not a
Transformer but it's enough to
illustrate the idea that directions in
the space can carry semantic meaning a
very classic classic example of this is
how if you take the difference between
the vectors for woman and man something
you would visualize as a little Vector
in the space connecting the tip of one
to the tip of the other it's very
similar to the difference between king
and
queen so let's say you didn't know the
word for a female Monarch you could find
it by taking King adding this woman
minus man Direction and searching for
the embeddings closest to that
point at least kind of despite this
being being a classic example for the
model I'm playing with the true
embedding of Queen is actually a little
farther off than this would suggest
presumably because the way that Queen is
used in training data is not merely a
feminine version of King when I played
around family relations seemed to
illustrate the idea much better the
point is it looks like during training
the model found it advantageous to
choose embeddings such that One
Direction in this space encodes gender
information another example is that if
you take the embedding of Italy and you
subtract the embedding of Germany and
then you add that to the embedding of
Hitler you get something very close to
the embedding of musolini it's as if the
model learned to associate some
directions with italianness and others
with World War II AIS leaders maybe my
favorite example in this vein is how in
some models if you take the difference
between Germany and Japan and you add it
to Sushi you end up very close to broadw
worst also in playing this game of
finding nearest neighbors I was very
pleased to see how close cat was to both
beast and monster one bit of
mathematical intuition that's helpful to
have in mind especially for the next
chapter is how the dot product of two
vectors can be thought of as a way to
measure how well they align
computationally dot products involve
multiplying all the corresponding
components and then adding the results
which is good since so much of our
computation has to look like weighted
sums geometrically the dot product is
positive when vectors point in similar
directions it's zero if they're
perpendicular and it's negative whenever
they point in opposite directions for
example let's say you were playing with
this model and you hypothesize that the
embedding of cats minus cat might
represent a sort of plurality Direction
in the space to test this I'm going to
take this vector and compute its dot
product against the embeddings of
certain singular nouns and compare it to
the dot products with the corresponding
plural nouns if you play around with
this you'll notice that the plural ones
do indeed seem to consistently give
higher values than the singular ones
indicating that they align more with
this direction it's also fun how if you
take this do product with the embeddings
of the words 1 2 3 and so on they give
increasing values so it's as if we can
quantitatively measure how plural the
model finds a given
word again the specifics for how words
get embedded is learned using data this
embedding Matrix whose columns tell us
what happens to each word is the first
pile of weights in our model and using
the gpt3 numbers the vocabulary size
specifically is
50257 and again technically this
consists not of words per se but of
tokens and the embedding Dimension is
12,288 multiplying those tells us this
consists of about 617 million weights
let's go ahead and add this to a running
tally remembering that by the end we
should count up to 175
billion in the case of Transformers you
really want to think of the vectors in
this embedding space as not merely
representing individual words for one
thing they also encode information about
the position of that word which we'll
talk about later but more importantly
you should think of them as having the
capacity to soak in context a vector
that started its life as the embedding
of the word King for example might
progressively get tugged and pulled by
various blocks in this network so that
by the end it points in a much more
specific and nuanced direction that
somehow encodes that it was a king who
lived in Scotland
and who had achieved his post after
murdering the previous King and who's
being described in Shakespearean
language think about your own
understanding of a given word the
meaning of that word is clearly informed
by the surroundings and sometimes this
includes context from a long distance
away so in putting together a model that
has the ability to predict what word
comes next the goal is to somehow
Empower it to incorporate context
efficiently to be clear in that very
first step when you create the array of
vectors based on the input text each
each one of those is simply plucked out
of the embedding Matrix so initially
each one can only encode the meaning of
a single word without any input from its
surroundings but you should think of the
primary goal of this network that it
flows through as being to enable each
one of those vectors to soak up a
meaning that's much more rich and
specific than what mere individual words
could represent the network can only
process a fixed number of vectors at a
time known as its context size for gpt3
it was trained with a context size of
248 so the data flowing through the
network always looks like this array of
20 48 columns Each of which has 12,000
Dimensions this context size limits how
much text the Transformer can
incorporate when it's making a
prediction of the next word this is why
long conversations with certain chat
Bots like the early versions of chat GPT
often gave the feeling of the bot kind
of losing the threat of conversation as
you continued too long we'll go into the
details of attention in due time but
skipping ahead I want to talk for a
minute about what happens at the very
end
remember the desired output is a
probability distribution over all tokens
that might come next for example if the
very last word is professor and the
context includes words like Harry Potter
and immediately proceeding we see least
favorite teacher and also if you give me
some leeway by letting me pretend that
tokens simply look like full words then
a well-trained network that had built up
knowledge of Harry Potter would
presumably assign a high number to the
word Snape this involves two different
steps the first one is to use another
Matrix that Maps the very last Vector in
that context to a list of 50,000 values
one for each token in the vocabulary
then there's a function that normalizes
this into a probability distribution
it's called softmax and we'll talk more
about it in just a second but before
that it might seem a little bit weird to
only use this last embedding to make a
prediction when after all in that last
step there are thousands of other
vectors in the layer just sitting there
with their own context-rich meanings
this has to do with the fact that in the
training process it turns out to be much
more efficient if you use each one of
those vectors in the final layer to
simultaneously make a prediction for
what would come immediately after it
there's a lot more to be said about
training later on but I just want to
call that out right now this Matrix is
called The unembedded Matrix and we give
it the label W again like all the weight
matrices we see it's entries begin at
random but they are learned during the
training process keeping score on our
total parameter count this unembedded
Matrix has one row for each word in the
vocabulary and each row has the same
number of elements as the embedding
Dimension it's very similar to the
embedding Matrix just with the order
swapped so it adds another 617 million
parameters to the network meaning our
count so far is a little over a billion
a small but not wholly insignificant
fraction of the 175 billion that we'll
end up with in total as the very last
mini lesson for this chapter I want to
talk more about the softmax function
since it makes another appearance for us
once we dive into the atttention
blocks the idea is that if you want a
sequence of numbers to act as a
probability distribution say a
distribution over all possible next
words then each value has to be between
0o and one and you also need all of them
to add up to one however if you're
playing the Deep learning game where
everything you do looks like Matrix
Vector multiplication the outputs that
you get by default don't abide by this
at all the values are often negative or
much bigger than one and they almost
certainly don't add up to one softmax is
the standard way to turn an arbitrary
list of numbers into a valid
distribution in such a way that the
largest values end up closest to one and
the smaller values end up very close to
zero that's all you really need to know
but if you're curious the way that it
works is to First raise e to the power
of each of the numbers which means you
now have a list of positive values and
then you can take the sum of all those
positive values and divide each term by
that sum which normalizes it into a list
that adds up to one you'll notice that
if one of the numbers in the input is
meaningfully bigger than the rest then
in the output the corresponding term
dominates the distribution so if you
were sampling from it you'd almost
certainly just be picking the maximizing
input but it's softer than just picking
the max in the sense that when other
values are similarly large they also get
meaningful weight in the distribution
and everything changes continuously as
you continuously vary the inputs in some
situations like when chat GPT is using
this distribution to create a next word
there's room for a little bit of extra
fun by adding a little extra spice into
this function with a constant T thrown
into the denominator of those exponents
we call it the temperature since it
vaguely resembles the role of
temperature in certain thermodynamics
equations and the effect is that when T
is larger you give more weight to the
lower values meaning the distribution is
a little bit more uniform and if T is
smaller then the bigger values will
dominate more aggressively we in the
extreme setting t equal to Zer means all
of the weight goes to that maximum value
for example I'll have gpt3 generate a
story with the seed text once upon a
time there was a but I'm going to use
different temperatures in each case
temperature zero means that it always
goes with the most predictable word and
what you get ends up being kind of a
trit derivative of Goldilocks a higher
temperature gives it a chance to choose
less likely words but it comes with a
risk in case the story starts out a bit
more originally about a young web artist
from South Korea but it quickly
degenerates into nonsense technically
speaking the API doesn't actually let
you pick a temperature bigger than two
there is no mathematical reason for this
it's just an arbitrary constraint
imposed I suppose to keep their tool
from being seen generating things that
are too nonsensical so if you're curious
the way this animation is actually
working is I'm taking the 20 most
probable next tokens that gpt3 generates
which seems to be the maximum they'll
give me and then I tweak the
probabilities based on an exponent of
1/5 as another bit of jargon in the same
way that you might call the components
of the output of this function
probabilities people often refer to the
inputs as logits or some people say
logits some people say logits I'm going
to say logits so for instance when you
feed in some text you have all these
word embeddings flow through the network
and you do this final multiplication
with the unembedded Matrix machine
learning people would refer to the
components in that Raw unnormalized
output as the logits for the next word
prediction a lot of the goal with this
chapter was to lay the foundations for
understanding the attention mechanism
Karate Kid wax on wax off style you see
if you have a strong intuition for word
embeddings for soft Max for how dot
products measure similarity and also the
underlying premise that most of the
calculations have to look like matrix
multiplication with matrices full of
tunable parameters then understanding
the attention mechanism this Cornerstone
piece in the whole modern boom in AI
should be relatively smooth for that
come join me in the next
chapter as I'm publishing this a draft
of that next chapter is available for
review by patreon supporters a final
version should be up in public in a week
or two it usually depends on how much I
end up changing based on that review in
the meantime if you want to dive into
attention and if you want to help the
channel out a little bit it's there
waiting
[Music]